Guide to the Stephen Harmon Photographs 1942, 1968-2017 PR 362
New-York Historical Society
Stephen Harmon photographs
1942, 1968-2017
New-York Historical Society
Harmon, Stephen F., 1943-
PR 362
758 Megabytes (3199 digital images in JPG format)
1.5 Linear feet in 1 flat box and 1 flat file folder
The collection includes over 3200 color photographs, primarily in digital form, taken by photographer Stephen Harmon (1943-) of New York City's buildings from brownstones to skyscrapers, storefronts, parks, people, and street life in the 1970s-2017. Especially well-represented in the collection are images of Times Square of the 1970s, Manhattan's Upper West Side, Central Park, Greenwich Village, the New York subway transit system and the passengers who ride the city's trains, and the city's street life from quiet side streets to traffic and pedestrian congested avenues. Additional images will continue to be added to the collection.
Arrangement
ORGANIZATION OF THE FINDING AID
For the purpose of presentation in this finding aid, the collection is described in nine series. The first eight series, designated with the prefix "D," are digital content and are organized broadly by topics that generally, and at points explicitly, follow Stephen Harmon's categorizations. The tenth series, designated with the prefix "P," includes photographic prints of various forms and subjects.
Series D.I. "Old Times Square" (1980s-1990s)
Series D.II. New York City Buildings, Parks and Other Cityscapes, prior to 2002 (1970s-2001)
Series D.III. New York City Buildings, Parks and Other Cityscapes, 2002 and later (2002-2017)
Series D.IV. "Street Portraits" (circa 1978-1988)
Series D.V. New York City "Street Show" (1995-2017)
Series D.VI. Subway Life (1980s-2017)
Series D.VII. Events (1968-2017)
Series D.VIII. Various Other Subjects (1970s-2017)
Series P.I. Photographic Prints (1942, 1970s-2011)
ORGANIZATION OF THE DIGITAL FILES
The digital files reflected in this finding aid were received by N-YHS in over 525 emails sent over the course of several years, from 2012-2017. Further, over 1000 emails and other transmissions received later have not yet been processed and will be added to the finding aid in the future. In part for this reason, the digital files are named, organized and stored in a chronological order (generally using date received) and not in accordance with the above series. For patrons requesting and receiving specific files, this difference will not matter. However, it will matter for patrons working more generally or with the entirety of the collection as they will need to use the chronological "digital folder" identifier, which uses a YYMMDD format, from the finding aid to navigate through the collection to locate specific images. The N-YHS Reference Librarian can provide any further guidance as needed.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen F. (Steve) Harmon is a now-retired attorney formerly of the Manhattan law firm Troutman Sanders and, most relevant for this collection, a lifelong photographer. Harmon was born in Brooklyn in 1943 and grew up in Queens. He graduated in 1964 with a B.A. from Queens College of the City University of New York and in 1967 with a LL.B from Brooklyn Law School. After residing for a time on Long Island, Harmon moved with his family back to New York City in 1978, living on the Upper West Side where he still resides with his wife, Cynthia. By the early 1980s, Harmon was a member of the SoHo Photo Gallery and exhibiting his work there and at other venues. His work is held by the Brooklyn Museum, Museum of the City of New York, New York Public Library, and other cultural and corporate collections in addition to the New-York Historical Society.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers in N-YHS's Reading Room by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
The digital files can be made available on-line for viewing only. To arrange to receive a link to the desired photographs, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the photographer, Stephen Harmon, at various times, primarily beginning in 2012 and continuing. Harmon's earliest gift was a set of eight photographic prints donated in 1983.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes color photographs of New York City, primarily in digital format, taken by Stephen Harmon in the 1970s to 2017. (Many photographs in digital formats from this time period and later remain unprocessed, and will be added to the finding aid over time.) The photographs tend to center on either the built environment of the city or the people who interact with the city and its built environment on a daily basis, though there is overlap between these categories. A particularly good example of this overlap in the collection is the series of "subway life" photographs, which include images of New York City's subway trains, stations, and the passengers who use them, often as an essential element of their urban lives and livelihoods.
Harmon's earliest photographs date from the 1970s-1980s and include images of Times Square, the World Trade Center, and people and fashions of the time. The latest photographs date into the 2010s, and include the Santiago Calatrava-designed Oculus at the World Trade Center Transportation Hub, the Gay Pride Parade of 2015, and many others. Ranging across these decades, and especially well-represented in the photographs, are images of Manhattan's Upper West Side, Central Park, and Greenwich Village, as well as many other areas of New York City. Manhattan predominates the collection, but Brooklyn, Queens, and the Bronx also appear.
Harmon transmitted the digital photographs, which comprise the bulk of the collection, via email over a period of 8 years, from his RCN webmail account to a New-York Historical Society Gmail account. The digital photographs are in JPG format, both born-digital and digitized by Harmon from original physical formats. Digital photographs were either attached to or embedded in his email messages and downloaded individually to local storage. Harmon's emails often included essential context for the digital photos that frequently went well beyond basic facts like date or building name to include backstory, commentary about the subject, humorous captioning, artistic intent and focus, and other deeper context. Accordingly, with only a few exceptions, the contextual emails were saved as PDFs and are included in the collection with the digital photographs.
Accruals
This finding aid includes the photographs that have been processed to date by N-YHS. Many digital files have not yet been processed and this finding aid will be updated as that occurs over time. In addition, the collection continues to receive new accessions from the photographer.
Central Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Times Square (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Color photographs.; Digital file formats.; Photographic prints.; Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Street life -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Subways -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.: 1970-2001)
- Series D.I. "Old Times Square", 1980s-1990s; 7.8 Megabytes (136 digital images in JPG format)
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes 136 images (transmitted in 1 email, which is also in the series) of Times Square taken in the 1980s to the mid 1990s. The title of the series comes from the subject line of Harmon's email.
  Most of the photographs depict the sex-themed entertainment orientation of the area during that period. These scenes include movie theater marquees and entrances featuring "XXX" erotic films and street level storefront signage for peep shows, burlesque, video stores, and other adult entertainment.
  The photographs also include images of other businesses in the area, including bars and lounges, hot dog and pretzel carts, retail storefronts, and restaurants, including Howard Johnson's and the Blarney Stone. The photographs are almost all of exteriors, with some interior lobby areas of movie theaters. Two photographs were taken inside the Colony Record Shop, which closed in 2012 after 64 years of business. Broader views of the area include large billboards and cars and traffic.
  The photos are jpegs. The email was saved as a PDF. Photographic prints from the photographer of many of these images are also found in Series P.1.
  Arrangement
  The photographs were received in one email and so are held in one digital folder.
  - Times Square (136 photos + 1 email), 1980s-1990s (Digital folder 20121002, Digital file 1_001-136, email)
- Series D.II. New York City Buildings, Parks and Other Cityscapes (prior to 2002), 1970s-2001; 64.5 Megabytes (187 digital images in JPG format)
  The series includes photographs of New York City buildings, storefronts and street views, primarily of Manhattan's Upper West Side. Also prominent in the series are over 60 photographs of the World Trade Center taken from various angles and distances over the years. The destruction of the Twin Towers in the attacks of 9/11 provides the chronological demarcation between this series and the next, and this series ends with two views of the burning towers taken from the 69th floor of the Chrysler Building. The series also holds several images of the East Village and SoHo areas of the 1980s-1990s, often emphasizing the graffiti and gritty feel of the areas before their gentrification in the early twentieth century. The specific scope of the series and the determination of which photos to include in it was made by the processing archivist.
  The series is arranged in rough chronological order by the date of the photographs.
  - World Trade Center / Twin Towers (26 photos + 1 email), 1970s-1990s (Digital folder 20151209, Digital file 1_01-26, email)
    Various views taken over time and from various angles and areas of the city.
  - World Trade Center / Twin Towers (36 photos + 1 email), 1970s-1990s (Digital folder 20170714, Digital file 1_01-36, email)
  - World Trade Center / Twin Towers (2 photos + 2 emails), 1980s (Digital folder 20171002, Digital file 1_1-2, 2 emails)
  - Midtown. 6th Avenue storefronts (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1975 (Digital folder 20160717, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - Forest Hills Tennis Club (1 photo + 1 email), 1977 September (Digital folder 20160714, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Various (4 photos + 1 email), 1978-1983 (Digital folder 20160715, Digital file 3_1-4, email)
    1) Upper West Side. Manufacturer's Hanover Trust bank entrance on northwest corner of 72nd Street and Broadway, October 1978. 2)Greenwich Village. 6th Avenue at Waverly showing Waverly Theatre marquee and storefronts, January 1983. 3) Upper West Side. Women on benches at Broadway and 75th Street, June 1982. 4)Upper West Side. Interior, slicing lox at counter at Zabar's, June 1980.
  - Upper West Side (2 photos + 2 emails), 1978, 1982 (Digital folder 20170224, Digital file 2_1-2, 2 emails)
    1) Median at Broadway and 75th Street, with women on benches. 2) Manufacturer's Hanover Trust bank entrance on northwest corner of 72nd Street and Broadway. (Dates given in email with duplicate images in folder 20160715.)
  - 79th Street Boat Basin (1 photo + 1 email), 1978 November (Digital folder 20170728, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - Upper West Side deli/produce shop window displays (2 photos + 1 email), circa 1978 (Digital folder 20170903, Digital file 2_1-2, email)
  - Upper West Side. Chatsworth (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1979 (Digital folder 20170106, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - Riverside Park; Dakota (3 photos + 1 email), circa 1979 (Digital folder 20170227, Digital file 1_1-3, email)
  - 42nd Street and 8th Avenue subway entrance (1 photo + 1 email), 1970s (Digital folder 20170314, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side storefronts (4 photos + 1 email), circa 1979-1987 (Digital folder 20170311, Digital file 1_1-4, email)
    1) Silver Palate on Columbus Avenue and 73rd; 2) P&G Café/Bar & Grill on Amsterdam Avenue and 73rd Street; 3) Big Nick hamburger joint on Broadway around 76th Street; and 4) Grossinger's Uptown Bake Shop.
  - SoHo. Foreplay Studios entrance (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1980 (Digital folder 20170127, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - East Village. East 10th Street doorway (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1980 (Digital folder 20170128, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Storefronts (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1980 (Digital folder 20170302, Digital file 2_1, email)
    South side of 72nd Street between Broadway and West End Avenue.
  - Railroad yard, Manhattan west side, south of 72nd Street (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1980 (Digital folder 20170718, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Storefronts on West 72nd Street between West End Avenue and Broadway (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1980 (Digital folder 20170728, Digital file 7_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. West 72nd Street storefronts (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1980 (Digital folder 20170811, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Famous Dairy Restaurant (1 photo + 1 email), 1981 (Digital folder 20171024, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - New York County Supreme Court House (60 Centre Street) (1 photo + 1 email), 1982 April (Digital folder 20160714, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - Midtown, 49th Street & 11th Avenue. Munson Diner & Checker taxi cab (2 photos + 2 emails), 1982 May (Digital folder 20170718, Digital file 3_1-2, 2 emails)
  - Rocco's pastry shop on Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1982 (Digital folder 20160717, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side, Amsterdam Avenue, Antonio's Barber Shop (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1982 (Digital folder 20170108, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side storefront (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1982 (Digital folder 20160803, Digital file 3_1, email)
    West side of Broadway at 78th Street, centered on Apthorp Laundramat.
  - Upper West Side. Broadway and 72nd Street (1 photo + 1 email), 1983 January (Digital folder 20160803, Digital file 6_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Blizzard of 1983 (4 photos + 1 email), 1983 February (Digital folder 20151219, Digital file 2_1-4, email)
  - Upper West Side. Blizzard of 1983 (1 photo + 1 email), 1983 February (Digital folder 20170329, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. West End Avenue, snow covered (1 photo + 1 email), 1983 (Digital folder 20160318, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Corner Book Store on West 72nd Street (1 photo + 1 email), 1983 April (Digital folder 20160803, Digital file 7_1, email)
  - Gramercy Park (22nd Street) (1 photo + 1 email), 1983 May (Digital folder 20170728, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side (3 photos + 1 email), 1983 (Digital folder 20160812, Digital file 1_1-3, email)
    1) 72nd Street subway station entrance with the Dorilton apartment building in the background on Amsterdam Avenue and 71st Street, December 1983. 2) Storefronts on the south side of 72nd Street between West End Avenue and Broadway, January 1983. 3) 277 West End Avenue, December 1983.
  - Street under elevated rail tracks (1 photo + 1 email), 1984 May (Digital folder 20170728, Digital file 6_1, email)
    Location is uncertain but appears to be in the Bronx, alongside Yankee Stadium.
  - Pan Am Building (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1984 (Digital folder 20170106, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Irving Place in the Gramercy Park area (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1985 (Digital folder 20170126, Digital file 4_1, email)
  - Upper West Side (3 photos + 1 email), circa 1985 (Digital folder 20170310, Digital file 1_1-3, email)
    1) Thalia theater front on 95th Street, 2) Johnny's book store front on Columbus Avenue around 86th Street, 3) Dorilton.
  - Upper West Side. 72nd Street Station on rainy night (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1985 (Digital folder 20170321, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Food cart by Dakota (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1985 (Digital folder 20170322, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - SoHo graffiti (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1985 (Digital folder 20170616, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Storefronts, West 72nd Street between Broadway and West End Avenue (2 photos + 2 emails), circa 1985 (Digital folder 20170713, Digital file 5_1-2, 2 emails)
  - Upper West Side. West End Avenue rowhouses (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1985 (Digital folder 20170808, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Central Park skylines (2 photos + 2 emails), 1986-1987 (Digital folder 20170728, Digital file 4_1-2, 2 emails)
    1) View of Manhattan east side skyline from within Central Park; 2) Wollman Skating Rink with buildings rising above the Park.
  - Upper West Side. Dublin House Bar (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1987 (Digital folder 20160322, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - East Village. St. Mark's Bar (1 photo + 1 email), 1988 March (Digital folder 20170728, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - Midtown. Playlands storefront (1 photo + 1 email), 1988 April (Digital folder 20151221, Digital file 1_1, email)
    Broadway, in upper 40s.
  - Upper West Side. Amsterdam Video adult film store (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1988 (Digital folder 20170317, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - SoHo (1 photo + 1 email), 1980s (Digital folder 20160321, Digital file 1_1, email)
    Unidentified grated building entrance.
  - Greenwich Village. Christopher Street doorway (1 photo + 1 email), 1980s (Digital folder 20161009, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Wm. Harnick Florist on 6th Avenue and 38th Street (1 photo +1 email), 1980s (Digital folder 20160716, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. H&H Bagels/Ballet school (1 photo + 1 email), 1980s (Digital folder 20160803, Digital file 2_1, email)
    Broadway at 81st Street.
  - ATM (automated teller machine) on Broadway (1 photo + 1 email), 1980s (Digital folder 20170302, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper West Side. Broadway Barber Shop (2 photos + 2 emails), 1980s (Digital folder 20170313, Digital file 1_1-2, 2 emails)
    Exterior storefront and interior.
  - Midtown. Mike's Barber Shop, 48th Street (1 photo + 1 email), 1980s (Digital folder 20170712, Digital file 4_1, email)
  - Storefronts (2 photos + 1 email), 1980s? (Digital folder 20160803, Digital file 1_1-2, email)
    1) Upper West Side. La Gran Esquina barber shop on Amsterdam Avenue at 82nd Street. 2) Greenwich Village. Newspapers, etc. store on Bleecker Street just west of 6th Avenue.
  - Canal Street storefronts (1 photo + 1 email), 1980s? (Digital folder 20170712, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - United Video & Camera storefront (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1990 (Digital folder 20160715, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Midtown. Skyline from Queens (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1990 (Digital folder 20170828, Digital file 2_1, email)
    View of skyline, with Empire State Building dominant, taken from 47th Avenue and 31st Street in Long Island City, which is in the foreground.
  - SoHo. Spring and Green streets, shop/flower display (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1990 (Digital folder 20171030, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - SoHo. 112 Prince Street (1 photo + 1 email), 1991 July (Digital folder 20151224, Digital file 1_1, email)
    Image of trompe l'oeil mural created by the artist Richard Haas in 1974.
  - Upper West Side (1 photo + 1 email), 1991 December (Digital folder 20151228, Digital file 1_1, email)
    Broadway and 72nd Street, looking southeast.
  - SoHo. Corner of Wooster and Broome streets (1 photo + 1 email), 1992 December (Digital folder 20170728, Digital file 5_1, email)
  - Lower Manhattan. Trinity Church (1 photo + 1 email), 1995 November (Digital folder 20170929, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - Upper West Side (8 photos + 6 emails), 1995 December (Digital folder 20170725, Digital file 1_1-8, 6 emails)
    1,2) Beresford on Central Park West (CPW) and 81st Street; 3) Museum of Natural History entrance on CPW; 4) buildings on CPW; 5,6) Amsterdam Avenue and Broadway between 70th and 71st streets; 7) West 75th Street, with the San Remo towers 8)CPW at evening, looking north from about 76th Street.
  - Grand Central Station, 42nd Street entrance, interior (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1995 (Digital folder 20170615, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Stage Deli (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1995 (Digital folder 20170616, Digital file 4_1, email)
  - Meatpacking district abandoned building (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1995 (Digital folder 20171018, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - 2nd Avenue Deli neon signage (1 photo + 1 email), 1996 March (Digital folder 20170201, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Hayden Planetarium (1 photo + 1 email), 1997 January (Digital folder 20171020, Digital file 3_1, email)
  - Central Park. Bethesda Fountain in snow (1 photo + 1 email), 1997 January (Digital folder 20171018, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - SoHo. Houston Street and Broadway (1 photo + 1 email), 1997 February (Digital folder 20171023, Digital file 1_1, email)
    With building mural advertisement for DKNY.
  - Central Park South skyline from the Park (1 photo + 1 email), 1997 May (Digital folder 20171020, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Statue of Liberty, at evening with crown and torch lit (1 photo + 1 email), 1997 May (Digital folder 20170929, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - Storefronts (3 photos + 2 emails), 1997 (Digital folder 20170713, Digital file 3_1-3, 2 emails)
    2 images of Russ & Daughters at 179 Houston Street and 1 of shops (shoe repair, barber, video) on Amsterdam Avenue between 73rd and 74th streets.
  - Chrysler Building (5 photos + 2 emails), 1997 (Digital folder 20170713, Digital file 4_1-5, 2 emails)
    4 views looking up with other buildings in foreground, and 1 skyline view with other Midtown buildings, from the Edward Koch Queensboro Bridge/59th Street Bridge.
  - Greenwich Village. Village Cigars (1 photo + 1 email), circa 1998 (Digital folder 20170126, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - SoHo. Green Street, graffiti-covered doorway (1 photo + 1 email), 1999 January (Digital folder 20171016, Digital file 2_1, email)
  - Broadway at 66th Street, snow-covered (1 photo + 1 email), 2000 December? (Digital folder 20170721, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Upper Manhattan. Broadway at 164th Street (4 photos + 2 emails), circa 2000 (Digital folder 20170127, Digital file 3_1-4, 2 emails)
  - SoHo. Spring Street (1 photo + 1 email), circa 2000 (Digital folder 20170127, Digital file 4_1, email)
    View from West Broadway looking east.
  - Katz's Deli and Russ & Daughters storefronts (2 photos + 1 email), circa 2000 (Digital folder 20170202, Digital file 1_1-2, email)
  - SoHo. Elizabeth Street, Albanese Meats storefront (1 photo + 1 email), circa 2000 (Digital folder 20170327, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - Coney Island. Parachute Drop (1 photo + 1 email), circa 2000 (Digital folder 20170621, Digital file 1_1, email)
    Deserted, foggy view.
  - Upper West Side. Royale Pastry Shop (1 photo + 1 email), circa 2000 (Digital folder 20170721, Digital file 3_1, email)
    72nd Street between Broadway and West End Avenue.
  - Contrasting Gothic church and modern office building (1 photo + 1 email), circa 2000 (Digital folder 20170815, Digital file 1_1, email)
  - World Trade Center. 9/11 (2 photos + 1 email), 2001 September 11 (Digital folder 20170126, Digital file 5_1-2, email)
    Two images of the Twin Towers burning, taken from the 69th floor of the Chrysler Building, with the Manhattan landscape in the foreground.
- Series D.III. New York City Buildings, Parks and Other Cityscapes (2002 and later), 2002-2017; 426.4 Megabytes (1571 digital images in JPG format)